You know, the title by itself could tilt
either way. Ketones are somehow harming
the liver and that's why we're having a
sicker liver. Or ketones are helping the
liver and the liver would otherwise be
sicker without them. Which is it? Well,
if you used a low carbohydrate diet
before or you fasted for periods of
time, you know that your liver produces
ketones, sort of pre- metabolized fat
molecules if you don't know what that
is. That being the case, it might be of
use to know why these ketones are
tracking with worse liver health shown
here. NAS or NAS is liver damage with
the further right indicating more damage
and the further up indicating more
ketone production. The line tracks up
and to the right indicating a
relationship between more ketone
production and more liver injury. That's
why I posed this initial question
because although we see this
relationship, we can't say that ketones
are actually causing the liver damage.
We can get answers to that by looking at
specific experiments that tease out the
direct effect like looking at animals
that have a genetic knockout or removal
of a key gene involved in ketogenesis,
i.e. the production of ketones. As these
animals are incapable of producing
ketones, this allows us to tease out if
the ketones are exacerbating the liver
damage or not. When looking at something
like liver weight, we can see the ketone
incapable condition, so the knockout on
the right versus those that do still
generate ketones. Clearly, the liver is
much bigger when ketones are not
present. So, is that a good thing? No,
probably not. Because when we look at
the contents of the liver, we're looking
at measurements of liver fat. Not
something that you want a lot of. As we
know from health conditions like fatty
liver disease in these images, the more
white and discoloration, the more fat
molecules are stored in and between the
liver cells, which we clearly see in the
ketoneless condition, confirmed in the
bar graph. So this all tells us that
while ketones associated with worse
liver health, the likelihood is that the
ketones are actually a protective
mechanism as removing them worsens liver
health. Pretty remarkable, right? Then
why? How is your liver using
ketogenesis? Remember that's ketone
production to protect itself from harm.
Well, when exposed to fat, your liver
uses a number of mechanisms to either
metabolize or export that fat. These are
normal processes. So for example, your
liver can burn the fat known as beta
oxidation or it could export it in fat
carrying particles like lowdensity
lipoproteins or it can produce ketones.
However, when your ketone production is
impaired, your liver now only has two
primary mechanisms to deal with the
influx of fat. Oddly enough, however,
while that might seem like enough,
ketogenesis seems to play a role as a
pressure release valve in a manner of
speaking for fat metabolism. The first
mechanism that we just discussed. I say
that because when ketogenesis is
impaired, fat metabolism, the beta
oxidation that we discussed, is also
significantly reduced. The short of it
then is your production of ketones by
your liver is not only acting as a
mechanism to deal with the fat molecules
being taken up from your diet and your
fat tissue by producing it into usable
energy, so ketones, but also allows the
normal fat metabolism of your liver to
function normally. All of that
culminates into less fat being
pathologically stored in your liver,
i.e. fatty liver disease. And if you
want even shorter explanation, ketone
production is liver protective. Now, I'm
going to get into an exciting
possibility related to what we went over
by marrying some human studies to the
research that we've just been relying
on. And there's another massive study
that goes into how a particular ketone
may play a uniquely protective role on
the liver. And there's much more to say
on what ketogenesis does inside your
liver cells that make it uniquely
protective, as well as some additional
considerations to keep in mind. That's
all covered in the insider version of
this video that you're watching. If you
want access to a whole video library
with more depth along with weekly
articles to accompany protocols and
guides, live sessions with me and more,
check out the link in the description
and join the mysterious land of the
physionic insiders.
And then you get in there and it's a
bunch of old people playing chess
talking about the weather. It isn't,
FYI. I mean, we can, but that's not the
most common topic. It's uh how to avoid
lower back pain. We're young and full of
life.
Okay. In fact, this is also proven true
in human trials and there might even be
preliminary evidence that ketones could
be an added benefit in combating liver
damage. I'm talking about these trials
among others that indicate very low
carbohydrate diets that raise ketone
levels do tend to improve liver markers
of health. But beyond that, in one
study, a ketogenic diet was compared
against a non- ketogenic diet. Only the
former raises ketones significantly, and
the results indicated greater fat
removal from the liver in the ketogenic
diet. Although both groups started out
with equivalent fatty liver disease.
That paired with the fact that the
researchers found a strong correlation
between elevated ketone levels and
reduced liver fat offers an exciting
possibility. Possibly a nutrition that
prioritizes ketone production could be
especially potent, even more so than
plain calorie restriction on removing
harmful fat from the inside of the
liver. And it's entirely possible it's
through this very mechanism of
increasing the fat molecule sync,
ketogenesis. In summary, a very low
carbohydrate diet could be uniquely
potent at reversing fatty liver disease.
It should be pointed out that the study
was very short, so it only offers a
glimpse into initial possibilities. But
there are studies lasting multiple
months that also indicate at the very
least benefits of low carbohydrate,
ketone promoting diets. But even so,
could we just raise ketones and get the
same effects? And how would we think
about all this for our own use? The
answer is no. We can't increase ketones
to mimic these benefits because we know
there's a lengthy metabolic consequence,
an inter relationship between these
different mechanisms of eliminating fat
from the liver. It's not only the
ketones themselves, but the production
of the ketones that lends itself to this
protective mechanism. It's a little like
the liver has to work for its health
like we do through exercise. There's no
exercise pill. you got to just uh work
for it and the liver does too. That
said, a very low carbohydrate diet,
which is defined uh a bunch of different
ways, but typically follows the rule of
less than 5% of your nutrition can be
carbohydrates of any sort. Some use
stricter guidelines of less than 20 gram
of carbohydrates. However, both will
likely raise ketones through the
necessary ketogenesis that we discussed.
The greater the carbohydrate
restriction, the more ketones are
produced. For those that fast, that's
the most potent way. So, all this put
together, we have evidence that yes,
increased production of ketones tracks
with worse liver health. But that is
likely because the liver is using ketone
production as a release valve to
eliminate as much of this unwanted
fattiness inside the liver. And in fact,
what human evidence that we have
suggests strongly that ketone promoting
nutrition like low carbohydrate diets
and fasting protect the liver, heal the
liver, and although more data is needed,
may be superior to other forms of
nutrition in supercharging the
elimination of unwanted fat from the
liver. And if you're on a quest for
eliminating a lack of health education
from your brain, this next video is well
known to do exactly that, you know.
Thanks for tuning in. Bye.